I'd like to tell you about a legal case that I worked on
أُريد أن احدثكم عن قضيه قانونيه اشتغلتها
involving a man named Steve Titus.
تمحورت حول رجل يدعى ستيف تايتس
Titus was a restaurant manager.
تايتس كان مدير مطعم
He was 31 years old, he lived in Seattle, Washington,
وكان يبلغ من العمر ٣١ عام وكان يعيش في مدينه سياتل في ولايه واشنطن
he was engaged to Gretchen,
وكان مخطوباً لغريتشن
about to be married, she was the love of his life.
وكانوا على وشك الزواج. وكانت غريتشين حب حياته
And one night, the couple went out
وفي ليله من الليالي, خرجا
for a romantic restaurant meal.
لتناول عشاء رومانسي
They were on their way home,
وفي طريق عودتهما الى البيت
and they were pulled over by a police officer.
استوقفوا من قبل الشرطه
You see, Titus' car sort of resembled
لأن سياره تايتس كانت تشبه الى حد ما
a car that was driven earlier in the evening
سياره رجل
by a man who raped a female hitchhiker,
قد قام باغتصاب فتاه على الطريق
and Titus kind of resembled that rapist.
وكان تايتس الى حد ما يشبه ذلك الرجل
So the police took a picture of Titus,
فصورت الشرطه تايتس
they put it in a photo lineup,
ووضعوها ضمن صور اخرى
they later showed it to the victim,
للعرض على الضحيه للتعرف على الجاني
and she pointed to Titus' photo.
وبالفعل أشارت الى تايتس
She said, "That one's the closest."
وقالت: "هذا هو الأقرب"
The police and the prosecution proceeded with a trial,
فقامت الشرطه والإدعاء باتهامه بالقضيه
and when Steve Titus was put on trial for rape,
وفي المحاكمه في قضيه الإغتصاب
the rape victim got on the stand
صعدت الضحيه الى منصه الشهاده
and said, "I'm absolutely positive that's the man."
وقالت: "انا متأكده تماماً انه الفاعل"
And Titus was convicted.
وثبتت التهمه على تايتس
He proclaimed his innocence,
واكد تايتس براءته
his family screamed at the jury,
وصرخت عائلته على هيئه المحلفين
his fiancée collapsed on the floor sobbing,
وانهارت خطيبته تبكي على الأرض
and Titus is taken away to jail.
وأخذ تايتس الى االسجن
So what would you do at this point?
فماذا كنت ستفعل في هذه اللحظه؟
What would you do?
ماذا كنت ستفعل؟
Well, Titus lost complete faith in the legal system,
تايتس فقد إيمانه بالنظام القانوني تماما
and yet he got an idea.
و مع ذالك وجد فكره
He called up the local newspaper,
اتصل تايتس بالصحيفه المحليه
he got the interest of an investigative journalist,
و شد إهتمام صحفي تحري
and that journalist actually found the real rapist,
و ذالك الصحفي وجد المغتصب الحقيقي
a man who ultimately confessed to this rape,
و في النهاية إعترف ذالك الرجل على جريمته
a man who was thought to have committed 50 rapes
رجلا يعتقد انه إغتصب 50 فتاة
in that area,
في تلك المنطقه
and when this information was given to the judge,
و عندما اعطية المعلومات للقاضي
the judge set Titus free.
اطلق صراح تايتس
And really, that's where this case should have ended.
و كان من المفترض ان تنتهي القضية هنا
It should have been over.
كان يجب ان تنتهي
Titus should have thought of this as a horrible year,
كان من المفترض لتايتس ان ينظر لهذه سنة كسنة مزرية
a year of accusation and trial, but over.
سنة اتهامات و محاكمة, لكنها انتهت
It didn't end that way.
لم تنتهي هكذا
Titus was so bitter.
كان تايتس يملؤه الحقد
He'd lost his job. He couldn't get it back.
لقد فقد عمله. لم يكن ليستعيده
He lost his fiancée.
فقد خطيبته
She couldn't put up with his persistent anger.
لم تستطع تحمل غضبه المستمر
He lost his entire savings,
لقد فقد جميع مدخراته
and so he decided to file a lawsuit
فقرر ان يرفع قضية
against the police and others whom he felt
ضد الشرطة والاخرين
were responsible for his suffering.
الذين كانو سبابا لمعاناته
And that's when I really started working on this case,
وهنا بدأت فعلا العمل على هذه القضية
trying to figure out
احاول معرفة
how did that victim go from
كيف تحول كلام الضحية من
"That one's the closest"
" هذا هو الاقرب"
to "I'm absolutely positive that's the guy."
الى "انا متأكده تماماً انه الفاعل"
Well, Titus was consumed with his civil case.
حسنا, تايتس كان منهمكا في قضيته المدنية
He spent every waking moment thinking about it,
قضى كل وقته بالتفكير فيها
and just days before he was to have his day in court,
و قبل ايام من موعده مع المحكمة
he woke up in the morning,
استيقظ في الصباح
doubled over in pain,
بألم شديد
and died of a stress-related heart attack.
ومات بنوبة قلبية جراء الضغط النفسي
He was 35 years old.
كان في ال35 من العمر
So I was asked to work on Titus' case
لذا طلب مني العمل في قضيته
because I'm a psychological scientist.
لأني عالِم نفسي
I study memory. I've studied memory for decades.
انا ادرس الذاكرة. درستها لعشرات السنين
And if I meet somebody on an airplane --
واذا قابلت شخصا ما في الطائرة..
this happened on the way over to Scotland --
.. هذا حدث في طريقي الى اسكوتلندا
if I meet somebody on an airplane,
اذا قابلت شخصا ما في الطائرة,
and we ask each other, "What do you do? What do you do?"
و نسأل بعضنا البعض "ماذا تعمل؟ ماذا تعمل؟"
and I say "I study memory,"
و اجيب " انا ادرس الذاكرة,"
they usually want to tell me how they have trouble remembering names,
في العادة يودون اخباري عن مشكلتهم في تذكر الاسماء,
or they've got a relative who's got Alzheimer's
او بأن لديهم قريب لديه مرض الزهايمر
or some kind of memory problem,
او نوع من انواع امراض الذاكرة
but I have to tell them
لكن علي ان اخبرهم
I don't study when people forget.
انا لا ادرس عنما ينسون الناس
I study the opposite: when they remember,
على العكس, عندما يتذكرون
when they remember things that didn't happen
عندما يتذكرون اشياء لم تحدث
or remember things that were different
او يتذكرون اشياء كانت مختلفة
from the way they really were.
عن الطريقة التي كانت عليها
I study false memories.
انا ادرس الذكريات الكاذبة
Unhappily, Steve Titus is not the only person
وللأسف, ستيف تايتس ليس الشخص الوحيد
to be convicted based on somebody's false memory.
الذي يدان بسبب ذكرى خاطئة لشخص ما.
In one project in the United States,
في مشروع ما في الولايات المتحدة,
information has been gathered
تم تجميع المعلومات
on 300 innocent people,
عن 300 اشخاص ابرياء
300 defendants who were convicted of crimes they didn't do.
و 300 متهمين تم ادانتهم لجرائم لم يقترفوها.
They spent 10, 20, 30 years in prison for these crimes,
وقد اتمو 10, 20, 30 عاما في السجن لهذه الجرائم,
and now DNA testing has proven
والآن فحص ال DNA قد اثبت
that they are actually innocent.
انهم فعلا ابرياء
And when those cases have been analyzed,
و بعد تحليل هذه القضايا
three quarters of them
ثلاثة ارباع منهم
are due to faulty memory, faulty eyewitness memory.
سببهم ذكرى خاطئة لشاهد عيان
Well, why?
حسنا, لماذا؟
Like the jurors who convicted those innocent people
مثل هيئة المحلفين الذين ادانو هؤلاء الابرياء
and the jurors who convicted Titus,
والمحلفين الذين ادانو تايتس,
many people believe that memory
معظم الناس تعتقد ان الذاكرة
works like a recording device.
تعمل كجهاز تسجيل
You just record the information,
انت فقط تسجل المعلومة
then you call it up and play it back
ثم تسترجعها و تعرضها مرة اخرى
when you want to answer questions or identify images.
عندما تريد الاجابة على سؤال ما او لتتعرف على بعض الصور
But decades of work in psychology
لكن سنين من العمل في مجال علم النفس
has shown that this just isn't true.
اظهر ان هذا غير صحيح
Our memories are constructive.
ذاكرتنا بنّائة
They're reconstructive.
ذاكرتنا ترميمية
Memory works a little bit more like a Wikipedia page:
الذاكرة تعمل قليلا مثل صفحة ويكيبيديا:
You can go in there and change it, but so can other people.
يمكنك الدخول اليها وتغيريها, وكذالك الاخرون
I first started studying this constructive memory process
في البداية بدأت دراسة تلك الذاكرة البنائة
in the 1970s.
في السبعينات
I did my experiments that involved showing people
لقد فعلت ذلك لبلدي التجارب التي تنطوي على عرض الناس
simulated crimes and accidents
محاكاة الجرائم والحوادث
and asking them questions about what they remember.
وطرح عليها أسئلة حول ما تذكر أنهم.
In one study, we showed people a simulated accident
في دراسة واحدة، ونحن أظهر الشعب حادث محاكاة
and we asked people,
ولقد طلبنا من الناس،
how fast were the cars going when they hit each other?
مدى سرعة السيارات التي تسير عندما تضرب بعضها البعض؟
And we asked other people,
وطلبنا من الآخرين،
how fast were the cars going when they smashed into each other?
مدى سرعة السيارات التي تسير عند أنهم حطموا في بعضها البعض؟
And if we asked the leading "smashed" question,
وإذا سألنا سؤال "حطم" الرائدة،
the witnesses told us the cars were going faster,
الشهود قال لنا السيارات التي تسير أسرع،
and moreover, that leading "smashed" question
وعلاوة على ذلك، أن تؤدي مسألة "تحطيم"
caused people to be more likely to tell us
بسبب الناس لتكون أكثر عرضه ليقول لنا
that they saw broken glass in the accident scene
أنهم شاهدوا الزجاج المكسور في مكان الحادث
when there wasn't any broken glass at all.
عندما لم يكن هناك أي الزجاج المكسور على الإطلاق.
In another study, we showed a simulated accident
وفي دراسة أخرى، ونحن أظهر حادث محاكاة
where a car went through an intersection with a stop sign,
حيث مرت سيارة في تقاطع مع توقيع على وقف،
and if we asked a question that insinuated it was a yield sign,
وإذا سألنا سؤال الذي ألمح إلى أنه كان علامة على غلة،
many witnesses told us they remember seeing a yield sign
العديد من الشهود قالوا لنا أنهم تذكر رؤية علامة الغلة
at the intersection, not a stop sign.
عند التقاطع، ليست علامة على التوقف.
And you might be thinking, well, you know,
ويمكن التفكير، حسنا، أنت تعرف،
these are filmed events,
هذه هي صورت الأحداث،
they are not particularly stressful.
فليست خاصة المجهدة.
Would the same kind of mistakes be made
وستبذل نفس النوع من الأخطاء
with a really stressful event?
مع حدث حقاً مرهقة؟
In a study we published just a few months ago,
في دراسة نشرناها منذ بضعة أشهر مضت،
we have an answer to this question,
لدينا إجابة على هذا السؤال،
because what was unusual about this study
لأن ما كان غير عادي حول هذه الدراسة
is we arranged for people to have a very stressful experience.
هو رتبنا للناس الحصول على خبرة مجهدة للغاية.
The subjects in this study
الموضوعات في هذه الدراسة
were members of the U.S. military
كانوا أعضاء في الولايات المتحدة العسكرية
who were undergoing a harrowing training exercise
الذين يخضعون تدريبات مروعة
to teach them what it's going to be like for them
لنعلمهم ما هو ذاهب ليكون مثل لهم
if they are ever captured as prisoners of war.
إذا من أي وقت مضى يتم القبض عليهم كأسرى حرب.
And as part of this training exercise,
وكجزء من هذه العملية التدريبية،
these soldiers are interrogated in an aggressive,
يتم استجواب هؤلاء الجنود في العدوانية،
hostile, physically abusive fashion for 30 minutes
أزياء معادية، وإساءة جسدية لمدة 30 دقيقة
and later on they have to try to identify
وفي وقت لاحق لهم في محاولة لتحديد
the person who conducted that interrogation.
الشخص الذي قام بإجراء هذا الاستجواب.
And when we feed them suggestive information
وعندما نقوم بتغذية لهم معلومات توحي
that insinuates it's a different person,
أن يلمح شخص آخر،
many of them misidentify their interrogator,
يخطيء الكثير منهم التعرف على المحقق،
often identifying someone who doesn't even remotely
وكثيراً ما تحديد شخص لا لو من بعيد
resemble the real interrogator.
تشبه الاستجواب الحقيقي.
And so what these studies are showing
وحتى ما يتم عرض هذه الدراسات
is that when you feed people misinformation
أنه عندما كنت إطعام الناس التضليل
about some experience that they may have had,
حول بعض الخبرة التي قد يكون لديها،
you can distort or contaminate or change their memory.
يمكن أن يشوه أو تلويث أو تغيير الذاكرة الخاصة بهم.
Well out there in the real world,
وهناك في العالم الحقيقي،
misinformation is everywhere.
التضليل الإعلامي في كل مكان.
We get misinformation
نحصل على المعلومات المضللة
not only if we're questioned in a leading way,
ليس فقط إذا كنا كنت شككت في طريقة رائدة،
but if we talk to other witnesses
ولكن إذا كان علينا التحدث إلى شهود آخرين
who might consciously or inadvertently feed us
الذين ربما عن قصد أو عن غير قصد تغذية لنا
some erroneous information,
بعض المعلومات الخاطئة،
or if we see media coverage about some event we might have experienced,
أو إذا كنا نرى التغطية الإعلامية حول بعض الأحداث قد شهدنا،
all of these provide the opportunity
كل هذه توفر فرصة
for this kind of contamination of our memory.
لهذا النوع من تلوث ذاكرتنا.
In the 1990s, we began to see
في التسعينات، بدأنا نرى
an even more extreme kind of memory problem.
نوع حتى أكثر تطرفاً من مشكلة في الذاكرة.
Some patients were going into therapy with one problem --
بعض المرضى الذين كانوا في طريقهم إلى العلاج مع مشكلة واحدة-
maybe they had depression, an eating disorder --
ربما كان لديهم الاكتئاب، واضطراب في الأكل-
and they were coming out of therapy
وأنهم كانوا قادمين من العلاج
with a different problem.
مع وجود مشكلة مختلفة.
Extreme memories for horrific brutalizations,
ذكريات متطرفة مروعة لأمور وحشية،
sometimes in satanic rituals,
في بعض الأحيان في الطقوس الشيطانية،
sometimes involving really bizarre and unusual elements.
في بعض الأحيان التي تنطوي على عناصر حقاً غريبة وغير عادية.
One woman came out of psychotherapy
خرجت امرأة واحدة من العلاج النفسي
believing that she'd endured years
الاعتقاد بأنها قد عانت سنوات
of ritualistic abuse, where she was forced into a pregnancy
من تعاطي الشعائرية، حيث أجبرت في الحمل
and that the baby was cut from her belly.
وأن كان قص الجنين من بطنها.
But there were no physical scars
ولكن كانت هناك لا ندوب المادية
or any kind of physical evidence
أو أي نوع من الأدلة المادية
that could have supported her story.
التي يمكن أن تدعم قصتها.
And when I began looking into these cases,
وعندما بدأت أبحث في هذه الحالات،
I was wondering,
وأتساءل،
where do these bizarre memories come from?
من أين تأتي هذه الذكريات الغريبة؟
And what I found is that most of these situations
ووجدت ما أن معظم هذه الحالات
involved some particular form of psychotherapy.
وتشارك بعض شكل معين للعلاج النفسي.
And so I asked,
وحتى سألت،
were some of the things going on in this psychotherapy --
وكانت بعض الأمور تسير في هذا العلاج النفسي-
like the imagination exercises
مثل تمارين الخيال
or dream interpretation,
أو تفسير الأحلام،
or in some cases hypnosis,
أو في بعض الحالات التنويم المغناطيسي،
or in some cases exposure to false information --
أو في بعض حالات التعرض لمعلومات كاذبة-
were these leading these patients
وكانت هذه في طليعة هؤلاء المرضى
to develop these very bizarre,
لتطوير هذه غريبة جداً،
unlikely memories?
ذكريات من المحتمل؟
And I designed some experiments
وأعد بعض التجارب
to try to study the processes that were being used
في محاولة لدراسة العمليات التي استخدمت
in this psychotherapy so I could study
في هذا العلاج النفسي حتى يمكن دراسة
the development of these very rich false memories.
تطوير هذه الذكريات الكاذبة غنية جداً.
In one of the first studies we did,
في واحدة من الدراسات الأولى التي قمنا به،
we used suggestion,
استخدمنا الاقتراح،
a method inspired by the psychotherapy we saw in these cases,
طريقة مستوحاة من العلاج النفسي رأيناه في هذه الحالات،
we used this kind of suggestion
قمنا باستخدام هذا النوع من الاقتراح
and planted a false memory
وزرعت ذاكرة كاذبة
that when you were a kid, five or six years old,
أنه عندما كنت طفلا، خمس أو ست سنوات من العمر،
you were lost in a shopping mall.
كنت قد فقدت في مركز للتسوق.
You were frightened. You were crying.
كنت خائفة. كانت تبكي لك.
You were ultimately rescued by an elderly person
يمكنك في نهاية المطاف أنقذت شخص مسن
and reunited with the family.
وبعد إعادة توحدها مع الأسرة.
And we succeeded in planting this memory
وقد نجحنا في زرع هذه الذاكرة
in the minds of about a quarter of our subjects.
في أذهان من حوالي ربع المواضيع لدينا.
And you might be thinking, well,
وقد يكون التفكير، حسنا،
that's not particularly stressful.
وهذا ليس خاصة المجهدة.
But we and other investigators have planted
ولكن نحن وسائر المحققين قد زرعنا
rich false memories of things that were
ذكريات غنية كاذبة من الأشياء التي كانت
much more unusual and much more stressful.
أكثر غرابة وأكثر إرهاقاً بكثير.
So in a study done in Tennessee,
أن في دراسة أجريت في ولاية تينيسي،
researchers planted the false memory
زرع الباحثون الذاكرة الزائفة
that when you were a kid, you nearly drowned
أنه عندما كنت طفلا، كنت تقريبا على وشك الغرق
and had to be rescued by a life guard.
ويجب أن يتم إنقاذه من قبل المنقذ.
And in a study done in Canada,
وفي دراسة في كندا،
researchers planted the false memory
زرع الباحثون الذاكرة الزائفة
that when you were a kid,
أنه عندما كنت طفلا،
something as awful as being attacked by a vicious animal
شيء كفظاعة التعرض لهجوم من حيوان مفزع
happened to you,
حدذ لك،
succeeding with about half of their subjects.
ينجح مع حوالي نصف من محل دراستهم.
And in a study done in Italy,
وفي دراسة في إيطاليا،
researchers planted the false memory,
زرع الباحثون الذاكرة الزائفة،
when you were a kid, you witnessed demonic possession.
عندما كنت طفلا، أنك شهدت لبس شيطاني.
I do want to add that it might seem
أريد أن أضيف أنه قد يبدو
like we are traumatizing these experimental subjects
أننا نعرضهم لتلك المواضيع التجريبية
in the name of science,
باسم العلم،
but our studies have gone through thorough evaluation
ولكن لدينا دراسات أجريت من خلال إجراء تقييم شامل
by research ethics boards
بمجالس أخلاقيات البحوث
that have made the decision
الت اتخذت القرار
that the temporary discomfort that some
أن عدم الراحة المؤقتة أن بعض
of these subjects might experience in these studies
من هذه المواضيع التي قد تواجه في هذه الدراسات
is outweighed by the importance of this problem
هو أقوى بكثير من أهمية هذه المشكلة
for understanding memory processes
لفهم عمليات الذاكرة
and the abuse of memory that is going on
وإساءة استخدام الذاكرة التي يدور
in some places in the world.
في بعض الأماكن في العالم.
Well, to my surprise,
حسنا، لدهشتي،
when I published this work and began to speak out
عند نشر هذا العمل، وبدأت في التحدث
against this particular brand of psychotherapy,
ضد هذا النوع الخاص من العلاج النفسي،
it created some pretty bad problems for me:
أنه خلق بعض المشاكل السيئة جداً بالنسبة لي:
hostilities, primarily from the repressed memory therapists,
الأعمال العدائية، أساسا من المعالجين ذووا ذاكرة مكبوتة،
who felt under attack,
وشعروا بتعرضهم للهجوم،
and by the patients whom they had influenced.
ومن المرضى الذين أثروا بهم.
I had sometimes armed guards at speeches
كان يحرسني رجال أمن مسلحون في خطاباتي أحيانا
that I was invited to give,
والتي دعيت إليها،
people trying to drum up letter-writing campaigns to get me fired.
أطلق الناس في محاولة بحشد حملات كتابة الرسائل لطردي.
But probably the worst
لكن ربما الأسوأ
was I suspected that a woman
كان أني اشتبهت أن امرأة
was innocent of abuse
برئة من الاعتداء
that was being claimed by her grown daughter.
ادعته ابنتها البالغة.
She accused her mother of sexual abuse
واتهمت والدتها بالاعتداء الجنسي
based on a repressed memory.
استناداً إلى ذاكرة مكبوتة.
And this accusing daughter had actually allowed her story
وقد سمحت الإبنة للقصة
to be filmed and presented in public places.
أن يتم تصويرها وعرضها في الأماكن العامة.
I was suspicious of this story,
كنت أشك في هذه القصة،
and so I started to investigate,
وهكذا بدأت بالتحقيق،
and eventually found information that convinced me
وفي نهاية المطاف عثرت على المعلومات التي أقنعتني
that this mother was innocent.
أن الأم كانت بريئة
I published an exposé on the case,
نشرت عرضا عن القضية،
and a little while later, the accusing daughter
وقليلاً في وقت لاحق، الإبنة صاحبة الإتهمام
filed a lawsuit.
رفعت دعوى قضائية.
Even though I'd never mentioned her name,
على الرغم من أني لم أكن لأذكر اسمها،
she sued me for defamation and invasion of privacy.
دعوتها كانت للتشهير وخرق للخصوصية.
And I went through nearly five years
وذهبت من خلال ما يقرب من خمس سنوات
of dealing with this messy, unpleasant litigation,
للتعامل مع هذه الدعاوى الفوضوية والغير سارة،
but finally, finally, it was over and I could really
ولكن أخيرا، أخيرا، أنها قد انتهت ويمكن بالفعل
get back to my work.
العودة إلى عملي.
In the process, however, I became part
في تلك الأثناء، ومع ذلك، أصبحت جزءا
of a disturbing trend in America
من اتجاه مقلق في أمريكا
where scientists are being sued
حيث يتم حاليا رفع دعوى ضد العلماء
for simply speaking out on matters of great public controversy.
ببساطة لأنهم يتحدثون في المسائل المثيرة للجدل .
When I got back to my work, I asked this question:
عندما عدت إلى عملي، سألت هذا السؤال:
if I plant a false memory in your mind,
لو أنني زرعت ذاكرة كاذبة في عقلك،
does it have repercussions?
هلو يكون لها مضاعفات؟
Does it affect your later thoughts,
هل تؤثر على أفكارك اللاحقة،
your later behaviors?
وسلوكياتك في وقت لاحق؟
Our first study planted a false memory
دراستنا الأولى زرعت ذاكرة كاذبة
that you got sick as a child eating certain foods:
أنك كطفل مرضت بتناول أطعمة معينة:
hard-boiled eggs, dill pickles, strawberry ice cream.
البيض المسلوق, المخللات, مثلجات الفراولة.
And we found that once we planted this false memory,
ووجدنا أنه بمجرد أننا زرعت هذه الذاكرة الزائفة،
people didn't want to eat the foods as much
لم يرغب الناس في تناول تلك الأطعمة بذلك القدر
at an outdoor picnic.
في نزهة في الهواء الطلق.
The false memories aren't necessarily bad or unpleasant.
الذكريات كاذبة ليست بالضرورة سيئة أو غير سارة.
If we planted a warm, fuzzy memory
إذا زرعنا ذاكرة دافئة وغامضة،
involving a healthy food like asparagus,
تحتوي على غذاء صحي مثل الهليون،
we could get people to want to eat asparagus more.
ويمكن أن نحل على الناس على أن تريد أن تآكل الهليون أكثر.
And so what these studies are showing
وحتى ما تعرضه هذه الدراسات
is that you can plant false memories
هو أنت يمكن زرع ذكريات زائفة
and they have repercussions
ويكون لها انعكاسات
that affect behavior long after the memories take hold.
التي تؤثر على السلوك الطويل بعد أن تترسخ الذكريات.
Well, along with this ability
حسنا، جنبا إلى جنب مع هذه القدرة
to plant memories and control behavior
بذرع ذكريات والتحكم في السلوك
obviously come some important ethical issues,
ومن الواضح أن تأتي بعض القضايا الأخلاقية الهامة،
like, when should we use this mind technology?
مثل، متى يجب علينا استخدام هذه التكنولوجيا في ؟
And should we ever ban its use?
وهل يجب أن نحظرها ابدا؟
Therapists can't ethically plant false memories
المعالجين أخلاقيا لا يمكنهم زرع ذكريات زائفة
in the mind of their patients
في عقل مرضاهم
even if it would help the patient,
وحتى إذا كان من شأنه أن يساعد المريض،
but there's nothing to stop a parent
ولكن لا يوجد شيء لإيقاف أحد الوالدين
from trying this out on their overweight or obese teenager.
من أن يجرب ذلك على زيادة الوزن أو السمنة على مراهق.
And when I suggested this publicly,
وعندما اقترحت هذا علنا،
it created an outcry again.
فقد أوجدت ضجة مرة أخرى.
"There she goes. She's advocating that parents lie to their children."
"ها هي تدافع عن كذب اآباء على أولادهم. "
Hello, Santa Claus. (Laughter)
مرحبا، سانتا كلوز. (ضحك)
I mean, another way to think about this is,
أعني، طريقة أخرى التفكير في هذا،
which would you rather have,
بدلاً من ذلك لديك،
a kid with obesity, diabetes, shortened lifespan,
طفل لديه سمنة ومرض السكري، وعمر قصير،
all the things that go with it,
كل الأشياء التي تجيء معها،
or a kid with one little extra bit of false memory?
أو طفلا بذكرى كاذبة إلى حد ما؟
I know what I would choose for a kid of mine.
أنا أعرف ماذا سوف أعتار لو كان طفلي.
But maybe my work has made me different from most people.
ولكن ربما عملي قد جعلني مختلفة عن معظم الناس.
Most people cherish their memories,
معظم الناس تعتز بذكرياتهم،
know that they represent their identity,
تعرف على أنها تمثل هويتهم،
who they are, where they came from.
الذين هم، من حيث جاءوا.
And I appreciate that. I feel that way too.
وأنا أقدر ذلك. ولدي نفس الشعور أيضا.
But I know from my work
ولكن أنا أعرف من عملي
how much fiction is already in there.
كم الخيال في الأمر.
If I've learned anything from these decades
إذا كنت قد تعلمت شيئا من هذه العقود
of working on these problems, it's this:
للعمل على حل هذه المشاكل، هذا:
just because somebody tells you something
فقط لأن شخص ما يخبرك بشيء
and they say it with confidence,
ويقولون أنه مع الثقة،
just because they say it with lots of detail,
لمجرد أنهم يقولون أنه مع الكثير من التفاصيل،
just because they express emotion when they say it,
لمجرد التعبير عن المشاعر عندما يصرحون بها،
it doesn't mean that it really happened.
وهذا لا يعني أن ذلك حدث بالفعل.
We can't reliably distinguish true memories from false memories.
لا يمكن أن نميز ذكريات حقيقية موثوقة من ذكريات كاذبة.
We need independent corroboration.
نحن بحاجة إلى أدلة مساندة مستقلة.
Such a discovery has made me more tolerant
هذا الاكتشاف قد جعلني أكثر تسامحا
of the everyday memory mistakes
من أخطاء الذاكرة اليومية
that my friends and family members make.
التي يصنعونها أصدقائي وأفراد أسرتي.
Such a discovery might have saved Steve Titus,
هذا اكتشاف قد أنقذت تايتس ستيف،
the man whose whole future was snatched away
رجل كان مستقبله كله سينتزع منه
by a false memory.
بسبب ذاكرة مزورة.
But meanwhile, we should all keep in mind,
ولكن في الوقت نفسه، ينبغي غلى أن الجميع يأخذ في الاعتبار،
we'd do well to,
أن نقوم بما علينا،
that memory, like liberty,
أن الذاكرة، مثل الحرية،
is a fragile thing.
شيء هش.
Thank you. Thank you.
شكرا. شكرا.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)
Thanks very much. (Applause)
شكرا جزيلا. (تصفيق)